Good morning, today is the second of ניסן. Nissan. It's, what, the
18th of March? My watch is wrong. אסרו חג ראש חודש,
Isru
Chag Rosh Chodesh, right?
There you go. We're starting the fifth פרק Perek today of עבודה
זרה. Avodah Zarah. We're on דף סב עמוד א, Daf Samech Bet
Amud Alef, right at the top.
Second day of state holiday in גלות. Galut.
I don't know. Is this the one? No, you could use that
one. So we're starting the פרק השוכר את הפועל. Perek Ha-socher Et
Ha-poel. We're continuing in the topic of wine produced or owned or
touched by non-Jews, but a little bit of a different focus here,
a little bit more on the monetary aspect, at least at the
beginning, we'll see.
Some other topics come up in the פרק Perek as well. Today
we're going to discuss besides the יין נסך Yayin Nesech question, the
question of שמיטה Shemitah fruits, as well as the prohibition of אתנן
זונה, Et-nan Zonah, which is a prohibition to bring an animal which
was used for payment for prostitution as a קרבן Korban in the
בית המקדש, Beit Ha-mikdash, which is an interesting topic and comes up
in only a few places, so it's a good place to discuss
it a little bit further. So, the משנה Mishnah says, השוכר את
הפועל לעשות עמו ביין נסך שכרו אסור. Ha-socher et ha-poel la-asot imo
be-yayin nesech secharo assur. If a person hires a worker, that is,
and רש"י Rashi helps us out already at the beginning, a non-Jewish
employer hires a Jewish laborer to work with him to do work
associated with the production of יין נסך, Yayin Nesech,
שכרו אסור, secharo assur, the wages are prohibited.
שכרו לעשות עמו מלאכה אחרת אף על פי שאמר לו העבר
לי חבית של יין נסך ממקום למקום שכרו מותר. Secharo la-asot imo
melacha acheret af al pi she-amar lo havir li chavit shel yayin
nesech mimakon lemakon secharo mutar. Even though one time he asked him,
"Hey, can you help me do this, you know, move this barrel
around?" or something like that, the wages will be permissible because in
general the official agreed-upon terms of the contract were for some other
work. We're going to see why is it that the Rabbis created
this prohibition that the איסור הנאה Isur Hana'ah extends even to the
level of the wages. Now we have a second case: השוכר את
החמור להביא עליה יין נסך שכרה אסור. Ha-socher et ha-chamor lehavi aleha
yayin nesech secharah assur. Someone rents out a donkey or hires a
donkey driver to transport
יין נסך, Yayin Nesech, the wages are prohibited. שכרה לשבת
עליה אף על פי שהניח עכו"ם לגינו עליה שכרה מותר. Secharah lashevet
aleha af al pi she-hinniach akum legito aleha secharah mutar. If you
hired the donkey in order to sit on it yourself and it
just happens to be that the non-Jewish person put the wine flask
on it or something else, then it's permissible because it wasn't the...
so basically the same message from both parts of the משנה, Mishnah,
that is, if it's some incidental one-time thing, it's not a big
deal, it's not going to be a problem, but if it was
the core reason why you rented or why you hired this donkey,
that's going to be a problem. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says,
מאי טעמא שכרו אסור? Mai ta'ama secharo assur? What? Ah, very good
question. So, it's basically the first question in the גמרא. Gemara. My
gut feeling would have been reading this משנה, Mishnah, I would think
it refers to סתם יינם. Stam Yeinam. We've seen throughout the מסכת
Masechet that the term יין נסך Yayin Nesech is used in place
of סתם יינם Stam Yeinam to emphasize or to exaggerate the level
of prohibition involved. That is, even the דרבנן De-rabbanan prohibition of סתם
יינם Stam Yeinam is referred to as יין נסך. Yayin Nesech. So
I would have thought the same thing here as well, that there's
even this prohibition of working with the, being hired out to be
involved in a non-kosher wine production, but the first question in the
גמרא Gemara is basically going to
say, יין נסך Yayin Nesech was a real problem.
Certainly. Certainly it's a real problem, continues to be a real, at
least a somewhat real problem. But the question will be, would we
take the prohibition to such an extreme by the דרבנן סתם יינם
De-rabbanan Stam Yeinam the same way we would for the דאורייתא? De-oraita?
So we see the גמרא Gemara compares יין נסך Yayin Nesech to
other איסורי הנאה Isurei Hana'ah like ערלה Orlah and כלאי הכרם. Kil'ei
Hakerem. So let's... מאי טעמא שכרו אסור? Mai ta'ama secharo assur? Why
is it that the wages are prohibited? אי לימא הואיל ויין נסך
אסור בהנאה שכרו נמי אסור. Ei leima ho'il ve-yayin nesech assur ba-hana'ah
secharo nami assur.
If you'll tell me the reason why is because the wine itself
is prohibited to derive any benefit from, then maybe you would conclude
the wages will be prohibited as well.
Fruits of the poisonous tree.
Okay. So הרי ערלה וכלאי הכרם דאסורין בהנאה, Harei orlah ve-kil'ei hakerem
de-asurin ba-hana'ah, but what about... we would find that ערלה Orlah and
כלאי הכרם, Kil'ei Hakerem, fruits from the first three years of a
tree's growth or כלאי הכרם, Kil'ei Hakerem, grapes that are grown in
a vineyard that are also growing wheat and barley? So דאסורין בהנאה,
de-asurin ba-hana'ah,
those are prohibited to derive any financial benefit from. ותנן מכרן וקידש
בדמיהן מקודשת. U-tenan mecharan ve-kiddesh bi-dmeihen mekudeshet.
However, the משנה Mishnah teaches regarding ערלה Orlah and כלאי הכרם Kil'ei
Hakerem that if you sold them, that is, you did end up
deriving financial benefit from them when you weren't supposed to, and then
the money you got for having sold the fruits you went and
used as money for כסף קידושין, Kessef Kiddushin, you went to go
get married using that money, מקודשת, mekudeshet, the woman would be considered
married. That is the money is not... remain prohibited. The money does
not carry the status of the prohibited items. So that's not a
good proof because then we would say, oh, if you just tell
me the reason is the איסור הנאה, Issur hana'ah, איסור הנאה Issur
hana'ah isn't good enough to get me to the point that the
wages should be prohibited because it should be the same as ערלה
Orlah and כלאי הכרם Kilay ha-Kerem that the money that's exchanged for
it should be okay. אלא הואיל ותופס דמיו כעבודת כוכבים. Ela ho'il
ve-tofes damav ke-avodat kochavim.
The reason why is not because of the איסור הנאה Issur hana'ah
on the object itself, but is because of the principle תופס דמיו,
Tofes damav, that it it claims, it grabs onto the money. That
is the status of whatever is being exchanged for lands on the
money itself.
No money laundering.
Something like you can't money launder it, so that is the money
that's exchanged for עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah itself, like if I buy
an idol, right, the money that was used for the or selling
an idol, the money that I get in exchange will have the
עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah status. So too if I sell יין נסך,
Yayin nesech, maybe the money will carry the same status as well,
it's תופס דמיו. Tofes damav. It's like, by the way, I don't
know, this is like Al Capone, financial spending, not the crimes themselves,
tax...
Right,
things like that. Right, so this kind of thing where you have
prohibited prohibited merchandise and you're wondering what's going to be the status.
We'll see that different different types of prohibited objects in הלכה Halachah
have different standing regarding this. Only certain things are going to have
this level of stringency of תופס דמיו, Tofes damav, that the status
latches onto the money itself. So הרי שביעית דתופס דמיה. Harei Shevi'it
de-tofes dame'ha. So what about the case of שמיטה Shmitah fruits? The
fruits grown during the שמיטה Shmitah year, that is they grew naturally,
they're from a tree or whatever, and the person who owns the
tree or anybody goes and picks the fruits,
but there's a prohibition of selling the fruits from שמיטה. Shmitah. שמיטה
Shmitah fruits are supposed to be for everyone to enjoy, everyone to
benefit from. They're supposed to be הפקר. Hefker. So even though I
have an apple orchard or whatever else, I'm supposed to let the
fruits go picked by whomever wants them on שמיטה. Shmitah. So if
I go and harvest most of the apples and I'm going to
go sell them in the marketplace, that's a big problem because what
have I done? I've done business with the fruits of שמיטה. Shmitah.
So the משנה Mishnah says האומר לפועל הילך דינר זה ולקוט לי
בו ירק היום. Ha-omer le-po'el hei-lech dinar zeh ve-likot li bo yarak
ha-yom. So if someone says to a worker, here, take one דינר
dinar and go pick vegetables for me today, that is during the
שמיטה Shmitah year, שכרו אסור. secharo assur. The the wages will be
prohibited for the same similar seemingly the same reason, that is תופס
דמיו, Tofes damav, the money grabs onto the same status. But if
he says לקוט לי ירק היום, likot li yarak ha-yom, שכרו מותר.
secharo mutar. If he just says, please go pick vegetables for me
today, and doesn't mention the wages explicitly, doesn't say how much he's
being paid, then the wages themselves will be permissible. That is it's
not so extreme as עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, where the money will
be grabbed onto whether it was implicit or explicit or anything like
that. So here, you have to mention the fact explicitly that you're
trying to do business with the שמיטה Shmitah fruits. Because seemingly you
could be doing me a favor, going to pick vegetables, and then
I could be doing you a favor and giving you a gift
for for no reason, right? We could have such a an arrangement
or or just a relationship. You do me a favor, I give
you you know I give you a gift, whatever, it wouldn't be
a sense of doing business, hired business, hired work to pick the
fruits of שמיטה. Shmitah.
Fruits of שמיטה Shmitah you can't plant, you can't do any or
any of the agriculture activities, but you can't benefit from the fruits
either, doesn't make sense.
You can benefit from the fruits, you're allowed to eat them. Why
not sell them? Why not? Because the so we're going to say,
the תורה Torah says that the fruits of שמיטה Shmitah are והיתה
שבת הארץ לכם לאכלה, ve-hayeta shabbat ha-aretz lachem le-ochla,
that the the fruits of שמיטה Shmitah and the rest for the
year is to be to produce food, but not to produce so
the rabbis understand לאכלה ולא לסחורה, le-ochla ve-lo le-sechora, that they're to
be eaten and not to be sold. It's for everyone. And it
should apply to everyone.
So it's not personal property either, isn't that right?
Right, the fruits itself the fruits of שמיטה Shmitah are considered הפקר
Hefker or they're ownerless, so everyone could claim them, even to go
onto someone else's property to pick to pick the fruits.
However, neither the fruit nor the property is yours, so you can't
sell it.
So the other thing that's important or interesting to note actually is
a bit of a debate between רמב"ם Rambam and רמב"ן Ramban about
the מצוה mitzvah to eat the fruits of שמיטה. Shmitah. רמב"ם Rambam
thinks that the מצוה mitzvah of לאכלה, le-ochla, that the fruits are
to be eaten, is just really is just teaching you the prohibition
of doing business with the fruits. רמב"ן Ramban counts in his addendum
to רמב"ם's Rambam's ספר המצוות Sefer HaMitzvot a separate מצוה mitzvah that
there is a positive מצוה mitzvah to eat the fruits of שמיטה.
Shmitah. And there are all sorts of interesting questions. I think הרב
קוק Rav Kook even said you're supposed to wash your hands before
eating שמיטה Shmitah fruits and things like that. It's some higher level
of קדושה. kedushah. It's some there is a question of should you
say a ברכה, bracha, a special ברכה bracha אשר קדשנו במצוותיו וציוונו
על אכילת פירות שביעית asher kidshanu be-mitzvotav ve-tzivanu al achilat perot shevi'it
or something like that. So those are at least points which get
discussed because of that debate. Charlie, what were you going to say?
Just the issue of taking them out of the Land of Israel.
Right, taking them out until the time of ביעור. Biur. After the
time of ביעור Biur then they could be exported, but that becomes
a question of when they are שמיטה Shemittah vegetables or things or
שמיטה Shemittah wine that makes its way to the United States or
oranges, I know there was a whole problem, אתרוגים Etrogim and also
the the Clementines that they sell at Costco come from Israel. So
you have to be worried about תרומה Terumah and מעשר Maaser also.
Anyway.
And actually they were selling אוצר בית דין Otzar Beit Din bottles
of wine in the supermarkets for a long time after.
Yeah well that's because wine wine keeps.
Okay but besides that there's an interesting issue here of it's a
little bit Marxist almost like who owns the not the means of
production but the the value of production because really nothing even if
he says לקוט לי ביום Lekot Li Bayom nothing is his that
it's his. Right it's not his.
Right. He just says hey you please go do the work for
me.
Implicit that there's a degree of ownership in the product.
I'm not even sure. I think it's just he's saying I'm going
to pay you compensate you for your labor. You're going to go
spend all day in the in the potato field, so you're going
to be the one sweating, you're going to be the one gets
dirty, so you should get paid. And I'm going to get the
potatoes, right?
But usually we talk that means you're trading your time for money.
But that's what he's doing. But the idea of the קדושה, Kedushah,
the גמרא Gemara is going to move away from the idea that
the קדושה Kedushah sticking to the money implies that to some degree
you're also trading the product.
Okay, right. So well that's exactly the question, which is the difference
between the first one. The first one
is הילך דינר זה ולקוט לי ירק היום, Heilach Dinar Zeh Velikot
Li Yerek Hayom, take this one dinar and go harvest fruits for
me today. That means the money is associated now with the fruits.
So the money is in some way grabbing onto the status of
the fruits as opposed to the second one where he just says
לקוט לי ירק היום Lekot Li Yerek Hayom go pick vegetables today
and implicitly I'm going to pay you compensate you for your time.
Yeah but you see if you use the potatoes for vodka or
the grapes for wine it's not immediate, it's it's.
That's a whole separate issue. That's a whole מסכתא. Masechta. Okay.
So אמר רבי אבהו אמר רבי יוחנן. Amar Rabbi Abahu Amar Rabbi
Yochanan. So we're going to have three attempts basically to deal with
this question of the comparison between יין נסך Yeyn Nesech and שמיטה,
Shemittah, that is the level why do they have differences in how
they're תופס את דמיהן Tofes Et Demeihen or how they associate the
prohibition or the status in the case of שמיטה Shemittah it's not
a prohibition but it's a status, the קדושה Kedushah of the fruits
is associated with the money or the wages involved. So the first
attempt is going to be from רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, then we
have אביי, Abaye, and then we have רבא. Rava. Okay. So אמר
רבי אבהו אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Abahu Amar Rabbi Yochanan, רבי
אבהו Rabbi Abahu quoted רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, קנס הוא שקנסו חכמים
בחמרין וביין נסך. Kenas Hu Shekansu Chachamim Bachamarin Ubeyeyn Nesech. There is
a special קנס, Kenas, a fine imposed, a deterrent imposed by the
Rabbis on חמרין, Chamarin, donkey drivers, and on יין נסך, Yeyn Nesech,
on non-Jewish wine. So יין נסך הדאמרן, Yeyn Nesech Hada'amran, יין נסך
Yeyn Nesech is what's already stated in our משנה. Mishna. That is
it's an unusual or unreasonable חומרא. Chumra. It was just the Rabbis
created this extra strict law as a deterrent, but it doesn't have
to flow logically from any comparison to some other הלכה. Halacha. And
that's why ערלה Orlah and כלאי הכרם Kilay Hakerem which are less
common and certainly less, you know, people have more of an aversion
to would be more less there would be less of a reason
to have this קנס, Kenas, and the case of שמיטה Shemittah could
be somewhat different. Okay. So יין נסך הדאמרן. Yeyn Nesech Hada'amran. חמרין,
Chamarin, what about the donkey drivers? מאי היא? Mai Hi? What case
are we talking about? דתניא החמרין שהיו עושין מלאכה בפירות שביעית. Detanya
Hachamarin Shehayu Osin Melacha Beperot Sheviit. What about donkey drivers who were
driving, who were transporting the fruits of שמיטה? Shemittah? שכרן שביעית, Secharan
Sheviit,
then the payment that they received will also carry the sanctity, the
קדושה Kedushah of the fruits of שמיטה. Shemittah. So מאי שכרן שביעית?
Mai Secharan Sheviit? What does it mean that their wages are now,
right? What does it mean for money to have קדושת שביעית? Kedushat
Sheviit? אי נימא דיהבינן להו שכר מפירות שביעית. Ei Nima Deyahavinan Lehu
Sechar Miperot Sheviit. So is it because you'll be they'll be paid
with fruits of שמיטה? Shemittah? נמצא זה פורע חובו מפירות שביעית. Nimtza
Zeh Porei Chovo Miperot Sheviit. That sounds like someone is paying off
a debt using שמיטה Shemittah fruits and that sounds like it would
be prohibited, that would be סחורה. Sechora. והתורה אמרה לאכלה ולא לסחורה.
Vehatorah Amrah L'ochla Velo L'sechora. The תורה Torah says you have to
eat them not to use them for business. So it doesn't make
sense to say that the wages will actually be paid using the
fruits. This is within רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan's explanation. ואלא דקדוש שכרן
בקדושת שביעית. Ve'ela Dekadosh Secharan Bikdushat Sheviit.
The money will retain the status of קדושת שביעית, Kedushat Sheviit, will
have the holiness of the fruit. ומי קדוש? Umi Kadosh? Are they
really considered קדוש? Kadosh? והתניא, Vehatanya,
but doesn't this ברייתא Braita say? קדוש Kadosh as the past verb
that they they sanctified.
כתוב Katuv like. כתוב Katuv they
wrote. Yeah. I don't
know if that.
Have they become. It's unspecified. It doesn't make such a difference. Okay.
והתניא האומר לפועל
הילך דינר זה ולקוט לי ירק היום. Vehatanya Haomer Lepoel Heilach Dinar
Zeh Velikot Li Yerek Hayom. Someone says to a worker take this
dinar and pick for me vegetables today. שכרו מותר, Secharo Mutar, the
wages will be permissible. לקוט לי ירק בו היום, Likot Li Yerek
Bo Hayom, שכרו אסור. Secharo Assur. So this is almost seemingly the
opposite version of what we just had.
Someone says דינר זה, Dinar Zeh, you take this money and go
pick vegetables for me today. שכרו מותר, Secharo Mutar, the payment will
be permissible. And if he
says It's kind of similar, just the words are different.
No,
but it's which status is opposite. I'm just taking a check. Anyways,
let's go on. The point is because the point is that the
שכר מותר s'char mutar is enough of a reason to say that
it's not that the money shouldn't be קדוש kadosh and that's why
רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan suggestion is now left hanging a little bit.
So we continue אמר אביי. Amar Abaye. אביי Abaye has another attempt:
לעולם יהבינן ליה שכר מפירות שביעית. Le'olam yahavinan lei s'char mi'peirot shevi'it.
So אביי Abaye says, I'll buy the first part, that is רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said oh it's a קנס knas that the Rabbis
imposed, and I'll buy the example you gave of the donkey drivers,
but I have to explain now what does it mean that the
payment for the donkey drivers is שביעית? shevi'it? So he says, oh
it means you get paid with the fruits of שמיטה shmita fruits.
Okay, יהבינן ליה שכר מפירות שביעית. yahavinan lei s'char mi'peirot shevi'it. ודקקשיא
לך לאכלה ולא לסחורה, Ve'dikshya lach le'ochla velo le's'chora, but didn't you
isn't it a problem that the פירות שביעית peirot shevi'it are supposed
to be used specifically for eating and not for business? דיהבינן ליה
בצד היתר. De'yahavinan lei be'tzad heter. You have to give it to
him in a way which is a permissible way.
כדתנן, Ke'detnan, לא יאמר אדם לחבירו העלה לי פירות הללו לירושלים לחלק.
lo yomar adam le'chaveiro ha'aleh li peirot halalu lirushalayim lechalek. A person
cannot tell his friend, here take these fruits of מעשר שני ma'aser
sheni to Jerusalem where they you have to eat מעשר שני ma'aser
sheni in Jerusalem. So he can't tell your friend, please take these
מעשר שני ma'aser sheni fruits to Jerusalem לחלק, lechalek, to sell them
there. Okay, 'cause that's going to be a problem of doing business
with מעשר שני ma'aser sheni fruits. אבל אומר לו, Aval omer lo,
you could tell him העלם לאוכלם ולשתותם בירושלים. ha'alem le'ochlam velishtotam birushalayim.
You can tell him, bring them with you to eat and drink
in Jerusalem ונותנין זה לזה מתנה של חנם. ve'notnin zeh la'zeh matana
shel chinam. And then they can give each other gifts. That is,
instead of hiring him to do it or telling him to sell
them, it's sort of like you can bring them to Jerusalem and
then you can do a gift exchange. Gift exchange is not the
same thing as selling. Even sort of culturally we get that.
Wait, but in the first part, where do you see that he's
selling them? לחלק. Lechalek. לחלק Lechalek doesn't doesn't it mean to distribute?
But it's to be distributed, but the problem
is probably לחלק, lechalek, you do the schlepping and then you get
the part of the fruit in Jerusalem.
No, look what רש״י Rashi says. שתטול שם חלק בהם, She'titol sham
chelek bahem, you're going to take a portion, דאסור לפרוע חובו ממעשר
שני, de'assur lifroa chovo mima'aser sheni, because there's a monetary exchange. The
fruits are being used for the payment. It doesn't mean they have
to sell them, I'm sorry, I corrected myself. I didn't mean he
has to be selling them in Jerusalem, but the sense that he's
getting a claim on the fruits as for payment for bringing them
to Jerusalem, which is a מצוה, mitzvah, so he shouldn't have to
be paid for it.
Okay, so you can give each other מתנה של חנם, matana shel
chinam, free a gift. That is, a gift exchange and selling something
or buying something's not the same thing. Okay, ורבא אמר. Ve'Rava amar.
רבא Rava disagrees with אביי. Abaye. רבא אמר לעולם דקדוש בקדושת שביעית.
Rava amar le'olam dekadosh bikdushat shevi'it. רבא Rava says that the money
will be קדוש kadosh with קדושת שביעית. kdushat shevi'it. So what does
it mean? ודקקשיא לך פועל? Ve'dikshya lach poel? So פועל דלא נפיש
אגריה לא קנסו רבנן. Poel delo nafish agrei lo kansu rabanan. Why,
so what about the ברייתא Beraita that says the difference between a
פועל poel who was hired to pick the vegetables and the חמר,
chamar, the donkey driver? So רבא Rava explains, the difference is פועל
דלא נפיש אגריה, poel delo nafish agrei, a worker doesn't usually get
paid very much, a day laborer who is working in the fields.
לא קנסו רבנן, Lo kansu rabanan, the Rabbis didn't make this קנס
knas against day laborers because they wanted to protect their wages.
However, they don't
get a if he gets hired to harvest שמיטה shmita fruits?
It's not skilled labor.
It's not a skilled laborer, חמרין chamarin have a certain level of
skill. You have to have training how to drive donkeys. I don't
know, it's not the same as driving a truck, but it's something
you still have to know what you're doing. It's some kind of,
right.
And we say לאכלה ולא לסחורה, le'ochla velo le's'chora, so we're saying
that's only on the person who owns it, not the...
Right. And what the point is, all of this is an assuming
that the discussion we're having here is the דרבנן de'rabanan problem. So
רבא's Rava point is לאכלה ולא לסחורה le'ochla velo le's'chora just means,
oh, so if you do סחורה s'chora with it, then the wages
or the payment is going to carry the קדושת שביעית. kdushat shevi'it.
That's the point, that's the consequence of you maybe violated the מצוה
mitzvah or whatever, but that's not what we're worried about here. What
we're worried about is whether there's this קנס, knas, whether the right,
whether we actually say that the wages are prohibited to get any
benefit from.
Okay, so what you're saying is that what, מדאורייתא mi'de'oraisa it may
still be אסור assur to do it, right? But there's no consequence.
It's over and on a לאו, lav, the שכר s'char would be
מותר. mutar. But then the
דרבנן de'rabanan קנס, knas, then the
שכר s'char would be אסור assur as well. Right, and that's the
difference between יינסך yayn nesech and שמיטה. shmita. So that's what we
see here, right?
They're so like concerned about יינסך yayn nesech as it's like ממש
עבודה זרה. mamash avoda zara.
Exactly, it's right here. And again, the question that יוחנן Yochanan asked
at the beginning, which is whether we're actually talking about יינסך, yayn
nesech, real יינסך, yayn nesech, or whether we're talking about סתם יינם,
stam yaynam, it's a little bit of...
רש״י Rashi says it's about יינסך.
yayn nesech. Right, but it's at least from reading the משנה, mishnah,
I wouldn't have I wouldn't know.
It says יינסך. yayn nesech.
It says יינסך, yayn nesech, but throughout... Maybe they use
it, but
they must have a reason not to.
Except throughout the מסכת masechet we've seen and we've been moving
from the דאורייתא de'oraita problems of עבודה זרה avoda zara into דרבנן,
derabanan, it's at least a question. It's at least a question.
When was סתם יינם stam yeinam enacted?
It was enacted sometime in the I would say probably the early
second temple period. It seems like at בית שמאי Beit Shammai and
בית הלל.
Beit Hillel. Not recent. Not recent.
I associate it with the medieval...
Right, well it certainly was in effect in the medieval times. There's
a lot of discussion of... Right,
there's a lot of discussion medieval times there were questions about well
how exactly do we what are some of the loopholes we can
employ to get around some of the prohibitions because Jews were involved
in the wine trade and things like that. Okay, so let's just
finish this bit of the סוגיא. sugya. ולא קשיא הך פועל. V'lo
kashya hach poel. What about the question of פועל poel that challenges
רבא's Rava's position? פועל דלא נפיש אגריה לא קנסו רבנן Poel d'lo
nafish agreh lo kansu rabanan because a פועל poel doesn't get such
high wages the Rabbis didn't impose this
קנס. knas. חמרי דנפיש אגרייהו קנסו רבנן Chamarei d'nafish agraihu kansu rabanan
but the donkey drivers the Rabbis imposed the fine because it's a
more lucrative position...
profession. I never thought they were so well compensated. I don't know.
Agricultural laborers are always the bottom. Here it's Mexicans, in Israel it's
Thai people.
Okay, so קנסו ביה רבנן. kansyu beh rabanan. ומתניתין U'matnitin but our
משנה mishna חומרא דיין נסך שאני. chumra d'yain nesech shani. So the
reason why our משנה mishna deviates from our expectation and prohibits even
פועל poel to work in the wine factory or whatever else the
sense is that that's because of the stringency applied to יין נסך
yain nesech not because there's any specific reason why שמיטה shmita would
follow the same paradigm. So שמיטה's shmita's sort of the guiding paradigm
the Rabbis created a special fine for donkey drivers, special stringency, and
then when they applied a similar logic to something like יין נסך
yain nesech they actually expanded the scope of that fine to even
include laborers as well. Okay, איבעיא להו. Ibaia lehu. So they ask
the question שכרו לסתם יינם מהו. secharo l'stam yeinam mahu. He hired
him to work...
It was obvious the first part was obviously about יין נסך. yain
nesech. Okay, right? There's no question.
At this point it's obvious but from reading the משנה mishna I
wouldn't have known. Right?
Though ultimately the אמוראים Amoraim read the משנה mishna they're not only
reading what's obvious. They could have just if they had a clear
idea of the answer to this question they would have read the
משנה mishna סתם יינם stam yeinam from the beginning.
Right. It would have had some other question. Right. So at least
at this point now, and this was Michael's frustration, but at least
by this point we're assuming that our משנה mishna is specifically about
real יין נסך, yain nesech, it's a real dyed in the wool
idolater who's been worshipping whatever and all of his wine is really
יין נסך. yain nesech. And now we have a question איבעיא להו
שכרו לסתם יינם מהו. ibaia lehu secharo l'stam yeinam mahu. Do we
have the same stringency regarding someone who's been hired to work in
a just a non-Jewish wine factory or whatever in that sort of
business? So do we say מי אמרינן כיון דאסיר חמור כיין נסך
שכרו נמי אסיר. mi amrinan keivan d'asir chamur k'yain nesech secharo nami
asir. Do we say that since the level of prohibition the Rabbis
imposed on סתם יינם stam yeinam is to treat the rabbinic prohibition
of the same stringency as the biblical prohibition we should say the
wages are also forbidden? או דילמא הואיל וטומאתו קיל o dilma ho'il
v'tuma'ato kil or do we say that because the level of טומאה
tuma that it transmits because עבודה זרה avoda zara specifically עבודה זרה
avoda zara is what transmits טומאה tuma but not things handled or
produced by non-Jews so it there is a leniency regarding סתם יינם
stam yeinam different from real יין נסך. yain nesech. So because טומאתו
קיל tuma'ato kil it's not as impurifying אף שכרו נמי קיל af
secharo nami kil so maybe we should say that...
So what do we what does one have to do with the
other?
That is what we're saying is how do we assess the comparison
between סתם יינם stam yeinam and יין נסך. yain nesech. Do we
say well they have the same level of prohibition they have the
same level of איסור issur or do we say actually they have
different rank regarding טומאה. tuma. Who cares? Because the question is do
we treat יין נסך yain nesech and סתם יינם stam yeinam as
equivalent or do we treat סתם יינם stam yeinam more leniently than
יין נסך. yain nesech. And the point is we have one example
for each where we at least have a paradigm to build on
for each.
All point is why the שכר sechar is אסור.
assur. Right. So right so we're asking a question did the Rabbis
when they were constructing this rabbinic קנס knas against the wages did
they model it after the ways in which סתם יינם stam yeinam
is equivalent to יין נסך yain nesech or did they model it
after the ways in which סתם יינם stam yeinam is more lenient
than יין נסך. yain nesech.
Right, I guess it's a weird way of saying it.
Yeah, but that's a גמרא gemara way of saying it.
Right?
You might even think that you'd be a little more lenient because
you know
at the end of the day... Does יין נסך yain nesech apply
to Catholics?
That's a big question that comes up throughout the מסכת. masechet.
Because then it would still be relevant in the Middle Ages.
Certainly.
That was exactly the question.
Okay, ironically what they use for sacramental wine is like Concord and
Manischewitz.
Yes. Okay, so תא שמע. ta shma. So to answer this question
consider the following.
דההוא גברא דאגר ארביה לסתם יינם. D'hahu gavra d'agar arbeih l'stam yeinam.
Someone rented out a boat to transport סתם יינם. stam yeinam. So
יהבו ליה חטי באגרא. yehavu lei chiti be-agra. The non-Jews to pay
him back filled up the boat with wheat. Seems like a pretty
good deal, right? You know, the rental fee, right? Wine is more
expensive than wheat, but wheat is a great payment for renting your
boat, right? So אתא לקמיה דרב חסדא. ata lekamei de-Rav Chisda. He
came to רב חסדא Rav Chisda and has the question, that is,
wait a second. He got into this business deal from the beginning
without even thinking about whether or not the wages were going to
be prohibited, right? So that's also interesting. He asked a שאלה, shaila,
right? Sometimes, thank God, people ask a שאלה shaila even when they're
worried the answer's going to be no. דאמר ליה da'amar lei זיל
קלינהו, zil kalinehu, go burn the wheat, וקברינהו ve-kavrinehu בבי קברי. be-bei
kivrei. Go and bury it in the cemetery. Okay. That is, first
burn them and then bury the ashes in the cemetery. So now
I want to read you the last משנה mishna in מסכת תמורה
Masechet Temurah with relevance also for upcoming פסח Pesach and
an important general principle about burying things and burning things. This is
תמורה Temurah פרק ז'. Perek Zayin.
Okay.
כל הקדשים שנשחטו חוץ מזמנן חוץ ממקומן הרי אלו ישרפו. Kol hakadashim
shenishchatu chutz mizmanan chutz mimkoman harei elu yisarefu. אשם תלוי ישרף Asham
taluy yisaref ורבי יהודה אומר יקבר. ve-Rabbi Yehuda omer yikaber. חטאת העוף
הבאה על הספק תשרף. Chatat ha'of haba'ah al hasafek tisaref. Okay. So
the last principle in מסכת תמורה, Masechet Temurah, כל הנשרפין, Kol hanisrafin,
everything which is required to be burned, לא יקברו lo yikaveiru should
not be buried. וכל הנקברין, Ve-chol hanikbarin, everything that needs to be
buried, לא ישרפו lo yisarefu should not be burned. That is, things
have an associated correct method of disposal. Burn or bury. One sec.
So רבי יהודה אומר אם רצה להחמיר על עצמו לשרוף את הנקברין
רשאי. Rabbi Yehuda omer im ratza lehachmir al atzmo lisrof et hanikbarin
rashai. Rabbi Yehuda says if you want to burn things which should
be buried, it's permissible. אמרו לו אינו רשאי לשנות. Amru lo eino
rashai leshanot. The other rabbis said back to him, you're not allowed
to do it. And the גמרא Gemara there discusses as well the
principle that, or
maybe it's even in the משנה mishna here.
One sec,
one sec.
I'll get to that. But the point is, generally we would say
כל הנשרפין, kol hanisrafin, everything that needs to be burned, אפרן מותר.
afaran mutar. If once you've burned it, you've fulfilled the מצוה mitzvah
associated with how to dispose of it, and therefore the dust or
the ashes or whatever will be permissible. And if we say נקברין,
nikbarin, it has to be buried, then כל הנקברין אפרן אסור, kol
hanikbarin afaran assur, that even after they've been decomposed underground, the dirt
remains prohibited because the purpose, right, burying something is getting rid of
it, is,
it doesn't transform the object, it just hides it away somewhere in
a sense. Burning it actually transforms it. We say פנים חדשות באו
לכאן. panim chadashot ba'u le-chan. When you burn something, the ashes are
considered a new item. So here, it sounds like, right, why is
רב חסדא Rav Chisda so מחמיר? machmir? He says you have to
burn it, and then you have to take the ashes and bury
them. So we're going to see. Okay. So לימא ליה leima lei
בדרינהו badrinehu אתא ביה בהו לידי תקלה. ata bi-hehu lidei takala. So
why couldn't you just say בדרינהו, badrinehu, throw them away, scatter them
away, scatter them around, right.
So because people are going to find them and come to wrong
ends because they're going to end up using these wheat which were,
which have the status of the סתם
יינם. stam yeinam. Okay.
ולקלינהו ולבדרינהו. Ve-liklinehu ve-livdrinehu. So why don't you just burn them and
then throw the ashes away? So דילמא מזבלי בהו. Dilma mizavlei behu.
Maybe people are going to use the ashes. So what's interesting there
is
like רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi שוחק וזורה
לרוח.
shochek
vezoreh laruach.
Okay. So we're, right. So in the ביעור חמץ bi'ur chametz question,
these are all interesting questions, and there's a piece from רב חיים
Rav Chaim about it exactly, how do we treat חמץ chametz as
נשרפין nisrafin or נקברין nikbarin and all these kind of questions. At
the end of the day, it sounds like no, we can flush
the חמץ chametz down the toilet or whatever else, as long as
it's not in your possession, right? We only burn חמץ chametz to
fulfill תשביתו, tashbitu, to remove the חמץ. chametz. That's what you do.
Exactly.
ערב פסח Erev Pesach on שבת. Shabbat. If you use a פליישיג
fleishig knife that you use for milk, do you burn
it, do you put it in the ground? So that's not really,
that's to take the grease off the surface. But
anyway,
okay. So the problem is, what if I throw the ashes into
the air? People are going to מזבלי בהו, mizavlei behu, people are
going to use it for fertilizer, because ash has a lot of
potassium, they're going to put it into their gardens. Okay. So the
problem seems like burning it isn't enough. That is, it wouldn't be
classified as נשרפין. nisrafin. So then the question is why do you
have to burn it if it's going to be נשרפין? nisrafin? So
he says ולקברינהו בעינייהו. Ve-likvarinehu be'einaihu. What?
You say why you have to burn it, it's going to be
נשרפין? nisrafin?
No, what I mean, why do you have to, right, if it's
נקברין, nikbarin, if it just has to be buried, why do you
have to burn it as well? So he says ולקברינהו בעינייהו, Ve-likvarinehu
be'einaihu, why don't you just bury them whole? So מי לא תנן,
Mi lo tenan, don't we have the משנה mishna says, אחד אבן
שנסקל בה ואחד עץ שנתלה עליו ואחד סייף שנהרג בו ואחד סודר
שנחנק בו, Echad even sheniskal bah ve-echad etz shenitlah alav ve-echad sayif
sheneherag bo ve-echad sudar shenichnak bo, all of the implements of capital
punishment, כולם נקברים עמו, kulam nikbarim imo, all of them are buried
alongside the person who is, has been executed by the בית דין.
Beit Din. So we had that in סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. So התם... Hatam...
So what are we trying to prove?
So it sounds like you can bury things and we're not worried
that people are going to dig it up and use it inappropriately.
That's not what we're worried about over there.
But they're אסור בהנאה. assur behana'ah.
Yeah, it's also like you don't see "Oh, this is the סודר
sudar that this guy was..."
But also because they're אסור בהנאה. assur behana'ah. It's a concern. Okay,
maybe it's a different concern. So התם דקקברי בבי דינא מוכח מילתא
דהרוגי בי דינא נינהו. hatam d'kakavrei b'vei dina mukeach milta deharugei bei
dina ninhu. So since they're buried adjacent to the בית דין, Beis
Din, the people will know that those graves are the graves of
people who were executed by the court and therefore they're not going
to go fussing around with the graves digging stuff up. Okay, הכא
לא
מוכח מילתא. hacha lo mukeach milta. If you just bury a huge
sack of wheat underground, people will find it, they're going to come
take the wheat. So אימר איניש גנב ואייתי קבריה הכא. eimar inish
ganav v'ayiti kavrei hacha.
So the people will just say this person was a thief and
he had a big bag of wheat and he buried it and
now I found it, so now I'm going to keep it for
myself and they're not going to know that it's אסור בהנאה assur
behana'ah and they're going to violate the prohibition. What's interesting about this
as well is that it raises the question about what about cases
of איסורי דרבנן, issurei d'rabbanan, rabbinic prohibitions that are committed בשוגג beshogeg
that you didn't even know. I had no awareness that this wheat
was prohibited or anything like that. Becomes an interesting question. There's a
classic comment of the נתיבות. Nesivos. I think it's in סימן ל"ו
siman lamed vav or something, I forget where it is exactly. The
נתיבות Nesivos makes a suggestion which which much debated and a very
interesting suggestion, but doesn't necessarily have all the best proofs, which is
that rabbinic prohibitions are only violated במזיד. b'meizid. Because all rabbinic prohibitions
stem from the מצוה דאורייתא mitzvah d'oraisa of לא תסור lo sasur
that you have to listen to the guidance of the Rabbis. So
it only makes sense to say that you're violating the Rabbis' prescriptions
if you do it willingly, if you do it intentionally, if you're
doing it out of malice, out of some level of rebellion. But
if you're just doing it accidentally or without consciousness or without knowledge
of the violation, then maybe you haven't actually violated לא תסור lo
sasur because you were unaware of what you were doing, which is
a very interesting idea. But then you have to deal with סוגיות
sugyos like this where it sounds like explicitly you have a rabbinic
prohibition that we're worried about people violating
unintentionally. Okay. So those were basically that was this discussion here of
this סתם יינם. stam yeinam. It sounds like רב חסדא Rav Chisda
was מחמיר machmir to say that the fruit, the wages, the rental
fee for using the boat to transport סתם יינם stam yeinam will
be prohibited אסור בהנאה assur behana'ah and we had to explain why
did he have to both burn them and then bury the ashes?
Is because if you just bury the wheat whole people are going
to find it and cause a problem. If you just burn it,
people will use the ashes for something. So really it's something that
needs to be buried, but we're also worried about someone digging up
the thing that got buried. Okay. דבי רבי
ינאי יזפי פירא דשביעית מעניים. d'vei Rabi Yannai yazfei peira d'shvi'is me'aniyim.
So the students of רבי ינאי Rabi Yannai would...
So like if this guy got paid in money then you'd have
to like
throw the money into ים המלח Yam HaMelach or something like that.
By the way ים המלח Yam HaMelach throughout the מסכת masechet I've
gotten
into a little bit of an excavation. ים המלח. Yam HaMelach. No,
so I got into a little bit of a debate with someone
about it. Davy Jones' Locker? I think it doesn't mean ים המלח
Yam HaMelach our ים המלח. Yam HaMelach. It means the sea or
it could be the Persian Gulf. It means throw them into the
sea. Doesn't mean throw 'em into ים המלח דווקא. Yam HaMelach davka.
So I got into a little bit of a debate with someone
about it because he said he had like a Twitter thing or
whatever it said like throw into the Dead Sea.
I
was like I don't
think it means דווקא davka the Dead Sea, right? Not everyone lives
near it. Davy Jones' Locker, right? Exactly. It should be the bottom
of the ocean, right? Where a place because you can't you have
to get rid of it in a way that it's going to
be gone forever. Now obviously things that are in the ocean could
be not gone forever, right?
Especially gold. Gold isn't going to isn't going to corrode. Gold will
stay under the ocean, people dig up gold coins all the time.
Right, I don't know all the time. But silver corrodes. Silver certainly
corrodes.
Have you know like research about ים המלח Yam HaMelach the connection
to what's it called Qumran and the...
What about oh what Qumran? It's about the decrease of
טומאה tumah and they all in the end...
Right right they went to a place near ים המלח. Yam HaMelach.
Yeah ים המלח דווקא. Yam HaMelach davka.
So it could be the phrase originated there.
Davy Jones' Locker.
That I don't know.
There may be some... sailors.
Exactly. But we all use it now. Right and we use that
phrase forever. Anyone who's seen Pirates of the Caribbean. Okay.
So דבי רבי ינאי יזפי פירא דשביעית מעניים ופרעו להו בשמינית. d'vei
Rabi Yannai yazfei peira d'shvi'is me'aniyim u'paru lehu b'shminis.
So people there are these people who would basically borrow against the
they would they would what would they do? They would take the
fruits from the עניים aniyim and give them the money. They would
borrow against the fruits of שביעית shvi'is on שמיטה shmita year and
pay back in the eighth year. So first... wait what would they
do?
It's lending money basically.
More or less.
It's the same word you can't tell if it's the lender or
the borrower.
Right.
Oh it means that the עניים aniyim are obviously getting the money.
So they lend the עניים aniyim but it's the fruits. I don't
know it's a little bit difficult. Are they using the fruits of
שמיטה shmita as the collateral for the loan or are they actually
giving them the fruits as a loan? It's a little bit odd,
but. But the point is, this is some kind of a loan
which is being contracted in the seventh year and being paid back
in the eighth year. And the point is, isn't that a problem
on the one hand of פירות *Peirot* of שמיטה *Shmita* produce? Okay.
So אתו אמרו ליה לרבי יוחנן *Atu amru leh le'Rabbi Yochanan*, so
they came to Rabbi Yochanan, said אמרו ליה *Amru leh*, יאות המה
עבדין *Yaot hema avdin*, they're doing properly, that is they did this
in such a way that they were, they were doing it to
benefit the עניים *Aniyim*. Why? Because the, let's think, basically to,
for the עניים *Aniyim* to lend against the fruits of שמיטה *Shmita*
because they could collect those fruits for free, and it's like getting
a loan for free basically, right? Michael, you're looking up what the
English is going to say to double check what I'm saying.
So you have to tell me.
That's what I'm trying to find where it
is.
It's toward the bottom of ס''ב עמוד ב' *Samech Bet Amud Bet*.
Yeah, no, I know, I'm just trying to find out where. Okay.
They borrowed the actual, they actually borrowed the fruits.
Right, that's what I was saying, right.
They borrowed the
fruits to pay back the, right, because the
שמיטה *Shmita*, the poor in the eighth year.
So that's my sense of what it was, is that the poor
people had gathered שמיטה *Shmita* fruits on the שמיטה *Shmita* year for
free, because it's הפקר *Hefker*. People come to them and say I
want to borrow two hundred dollars' worth of fruit from you, I
want to eat it now, so give it to me, and then
next year I'm going to pay you back two hundred dollars cash.
That is, a loan as if, but it's a loan against something
which you got for free. So it's a good way to support
the poor. It's actually and the, you know, talking about different ranking
of צדקה *Tzedakah*, it's a very high level of צדקה *Tzedakah* because
it's something that is not necessarily embarrassing or degrading for a poor
person to be involved with because it's actually a good, it's a
regular business venture. The problem is wait, you're doing business with the
שמיטה *Shmita* fruits, so that's the problem. So רבי ינאי *Rabbi Yannai*'s
students did it as a way, as a way of giving צדקה
*Tzedakah*, and the, they came to רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* to ask,
and רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* says they're doing it correctly. וכנגדן באתנן
מותר *U'knegdan b'etnan mutar*.
Why is that not a problem?
Because we're going to see. So it's going to come up, but
basically it's because the, because the monetary exchange is not happening in
time, but is with a delay, we don't consider it as a
real exchange. It's like a delayed gratification avoids the problem. So רבי
יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*, it's
not during the seventh year.
It's not, it's not just because not during the שמיטה *Shmita* year
itself, but it's because oh you give the fruits now and then
a year later you're going to get the money back is, is
a different kind of interaction. It's not selling.
Okay.
Fine, I borrow money from you during the שמיטה *Shmita* year and
say alright and you'll pay back money, pay me back fruits. So
is that any different?
I don't think it would be different, but that wouldn't benefit the
poor. That wouldn't be צדקה *Tzedakah*.
But no, so that's not doing business בפירות שביעית *b'peirot shevi'it*?
The question we could ask is was רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* saying
this is okay for everybody to do or is it specifically because
they wanted to find a leniency to support the poor? It seems
like from the way the justification is going to come up in
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, it sounds like the first one, which is
that it becomes, it's defended as a fully justified action and it
just happens to be that the students of רבי ינאי *Rabbi Yannai*
did it this way specifically as a particular benefit for the poor.
But it's a good question. Okay. So רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* had
said יאות הם עבדין *Yaot hem avdin*, they're doing it correctly, וכנגדן
באתנן מותר *u'knegdan b'etnan mutar*, and if you did the same thing
with אתנן Etnan *etnan*, then it's permissible. So first of all, let's
talk a little bit about אתנן *etnan*, we got to have another
foray into מסכת תמורה *Masechet Temurah*, this time in the third פרק
*Perek*.
So the פסוק *Pasuk* in the תורה Torah. *Torah* has two prohibitions
together, one is the prohibition of אתנן *etnan* and one is the
prohibition of מחיר *Mechir*, מחיר כלב *Mechir Kelev*.
One second.
No, it's the fourth פרק *Perek*.
So the fourth פרק *Perek* of תמורה *Temurah*.
Is this the fourth פרק *Perek*? No, it's the fifth פרק *Perek*.
Sixth פרק *Perek*, sorry.
פרק ו' משנה ג' *Perek Vav Mishna Gimel* or משנה ב' *Mishna
Bet*. איזו היא אתנן *Eizo hi etnan*? What is אתנן *etnan*? האומר
לזונה הא לך זה בשכרך *Ha'omer l'zonah ha lach zeh b'sichrech*. So
the person hires a prostitute and says this sheep, let's say, is
your payment, אפילו הן מאה *afillu hen me'ah*, or even a hundred
sheep, כולם אסורים *kulam assurim*, all of them become prohibited to bring
as a קרבן korban *Korban*. וכן האומר לחבירו הילך זה ותלין שפחתך
אצל עבדי *V'chen ha'omer l'chavero hach lach zeh v'talin shifchatach etzel avdi*,
or someone says take this sheep so that your slave woman will
sleep with my slave, male slave. ורבי אומר אינו אתנן *V'Rabbi omer
eino etnan*, Rabbi says that's not considered אתנן *etnan*, וחכמים אומרים אתנן
*v'Chachamim omrim etnan*, and the other Rabbis say that is אתנן *etnan*.
And then the next משנה *Mishna*, איזו היא מחיר כלב *eizo hi
mechir kelev*? What is מחיר כלב *Mechir Kelev*? האומר לחבירו הילך טלה
זה תחת כלב זה *Ha'omer l'chavero hach lach taleh zeh tachat kelev
zeh*, you say I'm going to make an exchange, you give me
a sheep, I give you a dog. וכן שני שותפין שחלקו *V'chen
shenei shutafin shechalaku*, two partners who together owned nineteen sheep and one
dog, אחד נטל עשרה ואחד נטל תשעה וכלב *echad natal asarah v'echad
natal tish'ah v'kelev*, one took ten sheep and one took nine sheep
and a dog, כנגד הכלב אסורים *knegad hakelev assurim*, the ten sheep
corresponding to the dog are prohibited to bring as קרבנות korbanos *Korbanot*,
ושעם הכלב *v'she'im hakelev*. מותרים *muttarim*, and the nine that go along
with the dog are permissible because they are only exchanged for sheep,
not for dog. אתנן כלב ומחיר זונה *Etnan kelev u-mechir zonah*, what
about if you take payment for
setting your prize dog out for stud? That's not prohibited money to
use for the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*. ומחיר זונה *u-mechir zonah*, or
money that was exchanged in this מחיר *mechir* way for a prostitute.
הרי אלו מותרים *Harei elu muttarim* are permissible, שנאמר *shene'emar*, שנים שנים
ולא ארבע *shnayim shnayim velo arba*,
because the פסוק *pasuk* says that only the two of them are
prohibited, not all four. That is only אתנן זונה Etnan Zonah. *etnan
zonah* and only מחיר כלב *mechir kelev*, but not מחיר זונה *mechir
zonah* and not אתנן כלב *etnan kelev*, which is also interesting because
there's an exchange between רב מנחם מנדל כשר *Rav Menachem Mendel Kasher*
and the ליובאוויטשער רבי *Lubavitcher Rebbe* about bringing service dogs into the
שול *shul*, and רב כשר *Rav Kasher* tried to be very מחמיר
*machmir* because he felt motivated by the logic of the מצווה *mitzvah*
of מחיר כלב *mechir kelev* to say that there's no place for
even, you know, he says מחיר כלב וקל וחומר כלב עצמו *mechir
kelev ve-kal vachomer kelev atzmo*, that the dog itself will be prohibited
because of this קרבנות *korbanot*. So it's about קרבנות *korbanot*, it's not
about going into the שול *shul*, and it's certainly we say we
don't make דרשות *drashot*.
לא תטע אלא קולץ *Lo tita
ela koletz*, it's the same logic, but we don't plant... Well actually
my friend Jason Strauss in Boston had a case, he had a
question about they wanted to put trees next to the שול *shul*,
he at least taught a whole שיעור *shiur* about it. But it's
an interesting
discussion. Obviously basically all of our שולן *shuls* will have trees somewhere
nearby, but the question is exactly why.
Anyway,
so what did the רבי *Rebbe* say? רבי *Rebbe* dog? So the
רבי *Rebbe* says it's prohibited for other reasons, but I have a
whole article that I wrote about service animals. I think there's a
very strong reason to be lenient. רב משה פיינשטיין *Rav Moshe Feinstein*
allowed it. Obviously, of course, of course, of course because you have
to be able... But there are many פוסקים *poskim* who were against
it and for a variety of reasons, at least in part because
none of these פוסקים *poskim*
were able to see anyway. Well, so certainly, right.
We got it a few times for ראש השנה *Rosh Hashanah* where
the בעל תוקע *ba'al tokeia* is blind and he gets onto the
בימה *bimah* with his dog. There you go.
Beautiful. Beautiful.
So
maybe they're aware of what the רבי *Rebbe* wrote and they don't
care or I don't know. I'll show you afterwards. So the משנה
דתניא *mishna de-tanya*, the ברייתא *braisa* says נתן לה ולא בעלה *natan
la velo ba'ala*. What about if a person pays a prostitute but
doesn't join up with her afterwards? או בעלה ולא נתן לה *o
ba'ala velo natan la*, or they were together but he didn't pay
her? אתננה מותר *etnana muttar*. Then her payment will be permissible. נתן
לה ולא בעלה פשיטא *natan la velo ba'ala pshita*. So if, so
wait a second, if he never paid her it's obvious that there's
no payment. No, he did pay her. נתן לה ולא בעלה פשיטא
*natan la velo ba'ala pshita*. If he gave her money without ever
having sex with her it's obvious, כיון דלא בעלה *kevan de-lo ba'ala*,
מתנה בעלמא היא *matana be'alma hi*, that's just giving her money, that's
just a gift, right? So that can't be אתנן זונה Etnan Zonah
*etnan zonah* דיהיב לה *de-yahiv la*. ותו בעלה ולא נתן לה הא
לא יהיב לה ולא מידי *ve-tu ba'ala velo natan la, ha lo
yahiv la velo midei*. And if you say בעלה ולא נתן לה
*ba'ala velo natan la*, they were together but he never paid her
for it, so then obviously there's nothing to be prohibited because he
never paid her. Okay. וכיון דלא נתן לה מאי אתננה מותר *ve-kevan
de-lo natan la, mai etnana muttar*.
So then what is the ברייתא *braisa* telling me is permissible if
there is no payment? Okay. So this ברייתא *braisa* seems to be
rather strange. That is the cases it's describing either seem impossible or
unnecessarily straightforward. אלא הכי קאמר *ela hachi kamar*, this is what the
ברייתא *braisa* means. נתן לה ואחר כך בעלה *natan la ve-acharkach ba'ala*,
he paid her now and they had intercourse sometime in the future.
או בעלה ואחר כך נתן לה *o ba'ala ve-acharkach natan la*, or
they had intercourse now and then he pays her sometime in the
future. אתננה מותר *etnana muttar*. The payment will be permissible for using
as a קרבן korban *korban*. נתן לה ואחר כך בעלה *natan la
ve-acharkach ba'ala*. So if he paid her and they had sex later,
לכי בעלה לחולי איסור אתנן למפרע *lechi ba'ala lechulei issur etnan le-mafre'a*.
Shouldn't we say that the prohibition of אתנן *etnan* will be... So
the אתנן *etnan* example is being used just to frame, clarify, this
example is being used to explain why it is that the שמיטה
*shemittah* fruits with this deal that the students of רבי ינאי *Rabbi
Yannai* made this loan to the poor people is okay because the
status can only take effect at that moment but not if there's
a time delay in between. So the אתנן *etnan* case as well
רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* said כנגדן באתנן מותר *k'negdan be-etnan muttar* that
if you did the same thing with אתנן *etnan* it would be
permissible because the time delay in between between the prostitution and the
payment.
I'm sorry, wait. So what's the problem then according to him? I
mean when is it אסור *assur*?
He seems to be saying אתנן *etnan* if you pay her right
now. Right now, well what's right now? Is it five minutes or
is it... we know the example of יהודה Yehuda, ותמר *Yehuda and
Tamar* from the תורה Torah *Torah*, he sends it for some later
date. So
I don't know all the details exactly what counts as right now.
I don't think it has to be right now right now, but
certainly is an interesting interesting question that is we're distinguishing between payment
at the moment and some agreement to pay in the future or
paid in advance is not going to have the same status. Again
because the prohibition, we're not talking about is prostitution allowed. Obviously prohibition
is prohibited. Question is whether the animal that's used to pay the
prostitute will achieve a status to be prohibited as a קרבן. korban
And that we have a pretty high threshold of it seems that
prohibition is very narrow scope.
Okay. So now the גמרא asks a question: לכי בא עליה ליחול
עליה איסור. lichi ba aleia lichol aleia issur. And right at the
top of ס"ג עמוד א, Samech Gimmel Amud Aleph, shouldn't we say
that there's a retroactive
status of אתנן that would take hold
retroactively if he paid in advance? Because the money is already or
the sheep has already been given over and now they're involved in
this prostitution that this status will take effect. אמר רבי אלעזר: Amar
Rabbi Elazar: כשקדמה והקריבתו. keshekadmah vehikravto. It's because the prostitute already took
the animal before they were together and brought it as a קרבן
korban before, so it could never have achieved the status because it
was given in limbo. Interesting.
They used barter. That's what you mentioned of money, of cash.
Especially because mentioned in the time of the תורה. Torah I'm sure
Charlie has more to say about that about when the coins were
invented. In the time of the תורה Torah there were no coins.
They had gold pieces and silver pieces, whatever, but certainly a barter
economy would have been very convenient for people, especially a farmer. Why
does a farmer ever have silver or gold? Right? You have sheep,
so you can pay with sheep. Right? יהודה, Yehuda right? יהודה tried
to pay תמר Tamar with a sheep, right? Even seemingly a wealthy
man who had a large flocks and things like that. So unless
you needed it, right, the value of gold and silver is that
you can transport them more easily, they are smaller. Right? We value—the
value we ascribe to them is a high density, right?
Yeah, there's a hint though because the תורה specifically uses the word
כסף, kesef, which really means sugar
silver, for
things like redeeming מעשר שני, ma'aser sheni, and silver was more common.
Gold was fairly rare for much of historical time.
And gold even, you know, in certain parts of Africa and certain
parts of South America was very prevalent, but otherwise in the Middle
East was used more for jewelry and decoration and less for currency.
Right. Okay, so אמר רבי אלעזר Amar Rabbi Elazar says כשקדמה והקריבתו,
keshekadmah vehikravto, that אמר רבי אלעזר Amar Rabbi Elazar the אמורא Amora
suggests that it must be that she brought the קרבן korban before
or before he was engaged in prostitution with her. היכי דמי? heichi
dami? אי דאמר לה קני לך מעכשיו. i de'amar lah kani lach
me'achshav. If—how is that permissible? Because then what? Maybe she's bringing a
קרבן korban? that belongs to him still because they haven't followed through
on the
deal. היכי דמי? heichi dami? אי דאמר לה קני לך מעכשיו. i
de'amar lah kani lach me'achshav. He says, acquire it from me now.
פשיטא דשרי. peshita deshary. That should be permissible because he just said
here, take the sheep, that's just a sheep, right? דהא ליתא בשעת
ביאה. deha leita beshaat biah. The sheep no longer exists at the
time that they have intercourse. ומתנה בעלמא הוא דיהיב לה. umatanah be'alma
hu de'yahiv lah. And it's just a gift, it's not אתנן זונה.
Like what he's trying to say is take
this, you know, it's
על תנאי, al tnai, and you know,
I'm not saying I'm going to need it because I—Right, but the
point is that to become אתנן זונה it has to actually be
number one, given in close proximity to the act of prostitution. Who
said that?
I mean, to me it doesn't sound so פשוט pashut at all.
Sounds like it's tainted. It's like, you know, and this is not
the kind of thing you want to bring before God. I don't
think God
is—But did you break the מצוה? mitzvah? I mean, you're really sitting
there saying, oh, well, you know, he technically made it out of
my rule, I'm fine with it. I think He'd be up there
fuming, you know, like—Of course.
There's a difference and with קרבנות certainly, there's a difference between things
which are prohibited or פסול pasul as a קרבן korban. and things
which—which God likes or doesn't like, right? The נביאים Nevi'im talk about
that a lot, the whole question of מצוה הבאה בעבירה mitzvah haba'ah
ba'aveirah comes up in exactly that question in מלאכי, Malachi, which is
that sometimes there are things which maybe technically would be permissible which
are nonetheless God doesn't like.
Right. This sounds like at best נבל ברשות התורה. naval birshut hatorah.
Okay, so it's an interest—it's an important question to explore. Okay.
Alternatively, maybe God only cares whether we keep the מצוות mitzvot or
not. Meaning, He's upset about the prostitution itself, but whether you brought
the sheep as a קרבן korban, or not, okay, whatever.
It sounds like if anything at best מצוה הבאה בעבירה. mitzvah haba'ah
ba'aveirah.
These are all interesting questions. Okay. ואי דלא אמר לה קני לך
מעכשיו. ve'idei lo amar lah kani lach me'achshav.
Is there any prohibition of the תורה of prostitution itself?
According to most ראשונים, Rishonim, yes. The prohibition of קדישה, kedeshah, the—right?
There are two מצוות, mitzvot, there's לא תהיה קדשה מבנות ישראל lo
tihyeh kedeshah mibenot yisrael and לא תחלל את בתך להזנותה. lo techalel
et bitcha lehaznotah. So a man has a prohibition of prostituting his
daughter and there's also a prohibition on women being prostitutes themselves, and
men.
That's very wide, seems very wide.
Certainly. They say it's the oldest profession.
I just last night read in the Arabian Nights in the Middle
Ages, a man prostituting—a very wealthy man prostituting his daughter and prepayment
for the services.
There you go. So let's just try to finish a little bit
of this discussion here before the time runs out. דהא דיהיב לה
deha de'yahiv lah ואי דלא אמר לה קני לך מעכשיו, ve'idei lo
amar lah kani lach me'achshav, if he did not say to her
acquire it now, היכי מצי מקרבה? heichi matzi makriva?
How could she
bring
the
קרבן? ואיש כי יקדיש את ביתו. ve'ish ki yakdish et beito. else
owns as a קרבן. So how is it
possible? אלא דאמר לה, Ela de'amar lah, the man said to her,
להווי גבך, L'havei gabach, keep the sheep
as collateral, as if, עד שעת ביאה, ad sha'at biah, until the
time when we are actually together, and there and at that point
you will acquire it. ואי מצטרך לך, V'ee mitztarech lach, if you
really need it, קני מהשתא, kani me'hashta, then you can acquire it
now. If you want to take it as a קרבן, acquire it
now. Right. Okay. So that's where we get up to. Right, his
prostitute.
Or if you're hungry.
Right. Okay.
So that's where we get up to.
Right. Keep your eyes on Shlomo.